<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.6.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2019-03-05T21:10:24+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/</id><title type="html">Homepage of Miretz</title><subtitle>Welcome to my personal website! I'm a senior analytics engineer, backend developer, data scientist and a hobby game developer. </subtitle><author><name>Miroslav Semerad</name><uri>https://miretz.github.io/about</uri></author><entry><title type="html">On Meaningless work</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/philosophy/2018/02/18/on-meaningless-work.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="On Meaningless work" /><published>2018-02-18T08:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2018-02-18T08:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/philosophy/2018/02/18/on-meaningless-work</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/philosophy/2018/02/18/on-meaningless-work.html">&lt;p&gt;I like reading books. Many people find them to be a good source of relaxation and enjoy stories which aim to kindle the childish imagination which is buried deep inside all of us. People might enjoy The Lord of the Rings, Harry Potter or The Hunger Games. Books that resonate with a large audience and their fantasy worlds inspired several movies. Mass production of merchandise and advertising makes sure that even those who never read the books or watch the movies know what the story is about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, I am a fan of a very different kind of literature. When you think about the typical stories in the current popular bestsellers, you realize that they are mostly one-off experiences. You will enjoy them while reading/watching, finish the consumption of the product and forget about them. The adverts everywhere will eventually make you sick of them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why is that? Maybe one of the reasons might be that these books and movies are for the most part meaningless. I don’t argue that they are a great way to pass time, but in the long term they are consumable products. There are no parallels, no important life lessons to learn and very little inspiration in them that you could draw into your own life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-house-of-the-dead&quot;&gt;The House of the Dead&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am currently reading &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_House_of_the_Dead_(novel)&quot;&gt;The House of the Dead by Fyodor Dostojevskij&lt;/a&gt;. While the name of the book might sound like an old horror video-game, actually this book was written in 1862 and it has nothing to do with the horror genre. The House of the Dead is about the hard life in a prison camp in Siberia. The main protagonist and narrator Aleksandr Petrovich has been sentenced to ten years of hard labour. The book is a deep analysis of life and work, human soul, values and spirit. I’m pretty sure this book changes ones perspective on life after he reads it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One specific passage resonated a lot with me. It was about the prisoner’s point of view on meaningless work. To clarify, the inmates were paid regular money to do all the jobs. It was a smaller amount than in the real world but it was actual money. This work should have been positive for them, judging by their financial situation, but it was not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why is that? Let’s imagine filling a bucket and pouring it out and then filling it again. Repeating this over and over. The agony of such work would be far worse than anything else with regards to their life in captivity. Doing repetitive and meaningless work is probably the hardest punishment there is. The inmates rather chose hard work like building roads or mining, because it was not so repetitive and there were actual results which one could be proud of.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It once came into my head that if it were desired to reduce a man to nothing—to punish him atrociously, to crush him in such a manner that the most hardened murderer would tremble before such a punishment, and take fright beforehand—it would be necessary to give to his work a character of complete uselessness, even to absurdity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;modern-corporate-work&quot;&gt;Modern corporate work&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is not such a big stretch, if we draw a parallel to the modern corporate work. How many jobs might be meaningless or seem meaningless from the outset. What does this type of work do to us? David Graeber in his book &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bullshit_Jobs&quot;&gt;Bullshit Jobs: A theory&lt;/a&gt; talks a lot about the harm caused by meaningless jobs. He even categorizes the jobs into 5 types:  flunkies, goons, duct tapers, box tickers, and taskmasters. If you want to know more about these types I highly recommend that you read this book. It might even open your eyes and make changes that will eventually make you more happy in your current work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meaningless work is one of the biggest reasons why senior staff leaves their current employer. While junior people might be driven by money, the experienced people know that they will not get a huge salary increase if they go somewhere else. They leave their manager or they leave their meaningless job for a job in a fresh new company, interesting startup or start their own business.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what can we do to retain senior staff and reduce meaningless jobs? It’s simple, create meaningful jobs. Why are there so many developers working on Open Source projects? The work they are doing is meaningful and without their contributions a lot of the corporate software would never exist. They have real users and even real customers. Great many people are still doing this hard and demanding job absolutely for free. When the result of your work is internal reward (something to be proud of) it instantly becomes more meaningful (to you and to others).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-bottom-line&quot;&gt;The bottom line&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bottom line is that if you want your employees to be happy, give them work which has a meaning. Give them work which is inspiring and which rewards their efforts. Work which is dynamic, open and where they can truly express their creative freedom. Allow them to speak to the clients or customers. Let them do the important choices. Give them responsibility for their own ideas and not just for their manager’s ideas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Leave the boring stuff for &lt;a href=&quot;https://automatetheboringstuff.com&quot;&gt;automation&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Miroslav Semerad</name><uri>https://miretz.github.io/about</uri></author><summary type="html">I like reading books. Many people find them to be a good source of relaxation and enjoy stories which aim to kindle the childish imagination which is buried deep inside all of us. People might enjoy The Lord of the Rings, Harry Potter or The Hunger Games. Books that resonate with a large audience and their fantasy worlds inspired several movies. Mass production of merchandise and advertising makes sure that even those who never read the books or watch the movies know what the story is about.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">How to manage software quality</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/management/2018/02/18/how-to-manage-software-quality.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How to manage software quality" /><published>2018-02-18T08:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2018-02-18T08:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/management/2018/02/18/how-to-manage-software-quality</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/management/2018/02/18/how-to-manage-software-quality.html">&lt;p&gt;At the heart of the software project lifecycle is the development phase. I have described how projects get to this phase in my previous post on &lt;a href=&quot;/management/2018/02/13/starting-new-projects.html&quot;&gt;How to start new projects&lt;/a&gt;. In this article I’m going to dive deeper into the development phase with focus on how to prevent project failures due to insufficient software quality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As with many things in the industry, it starts with the right mindset. So what is this software quality mindset?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;software-quality-mindset&quot;&gt;Software quality mindset&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a common mistake made by some software developers and managers. They often &lt;strong&gt;forget about software quality&lt;/strong&gt; as a part of the development process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many developers tend to believe that their code is so perfect that they do not need any quality checks. They estimate the time needed to write a feature and do not include any time for writing or updating tests. Later the code fails horribly in production due to a trivial and totally avoidable error. &lt;strong&gt;Believing in code quality is not enough. It has to be measured.&lt;/strong&gt; Code quality is the &lt;strong&gt;responsibility of the developer&lt;/strong&gt; when implementing new features.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is also typical for the project managers, IT leads and CTO’s. They often overlook the fact that their projects have no software quality measurements and do not enforce them. They might blindly trust their developers (or external vendors) to do the right thing and never even ask about it. Asking the developers about software quality could be uncomfortable, but it is necessary. The time estimates should include the time needed to ensure software quality. &lt;strong&gt;The manager is responsible for the overall quality of the software product.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having the software quality mindset means that both developers and managers actively measure and prevent any technical issues with the software. Having a dedicated &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Quality_assurance&quot;&gt;Quality assurance&lt;/a&gt; person on the team is good, but quality should be measured on all levels. Software projects  should try to avoid the creation and accumulation of &lt;strong&gt;technical debt&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;technical-debt&quot;&gt;Technical debt&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Technical debt is the potential cost of having to do any additional rework. Lack of quality measurements is one of the causes for its accumulation. It is very hard to eliminate it in later stages of the development and it might become a major reason for a complete rewrite or even cancellation of the project as dealing with the debt becomes too expensive. Managing technical debt is at the core of high quality software development. Developers can help reduce the technical debt by actively maintaining a suite of &lt;strong&gt;unit tests&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;unit-tests&quot;&gt;Unit tests&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unit tests are small scale procedures (in code) written by the developer to verify the functionality and capture any potential mistakes. They are focused on the smallest testable part of an application. The unit could be an individual function, module or a particular feature. These tests should be the primary quality checks for the developer. They enable to &lt;strong&gt;test the correct “happy path”&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;also other “problematic paths”&lt;/strong&gt; to see how the code behaves in these scenarios.
A well maintained test suite also helps new developers to quickly understand what each part of the code is doing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;There are too many ways a part of the code could break. Having an automated test that covers most of the possible scenarios is very beneficial.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Important tool in unit testing is &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mock_object&quot;&gt;Mocking&lt;/a&gt;. In general it means replacing components of the application with a mimic version for running tests. For example replacing a real database connection with a fake connection which acts as a real database. If the component cannot be properly mocked it could be an indicator that our code is not modular enough and this might become a problem in the future (&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Code_smell&quot;&gt;Code Smell&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The other big benefit is that executing a suite of unit tests is much faster than building and deploying the entire application.
This enables the developer to do small changes and test them rapidly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Test-driven_development&quot;&gt;Test-driven development&lt;/a&gt; is one of the popular approaches the developers could choose. In TDD the tests are written before the actual code. The adoption of the methodology really depends on the team. In the end what is important is the the software has a reasonable amount of &lt;strong&gt;code coverage&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;code-coverage&quot;&gt;Code coverage&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Code coverage is measured as a percentage of tested vs. untested code. Various tools can measure this automatically and even highlight the parts of the code which are not covered. There are many ways to configure the code coverage for different languages and editors. For example, for &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.jetbrains.com/pycharm/&quot;&gt;PyCharm&lt;/a&gt; there is a section in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.jetbrains.com/help/pycharm/configuring-code-coverage-measurement.html&quot;&gt;documentation&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For different editors there are other settings, plugins or standalone tools that enable code coverage measuring.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also a standalone &lt;strong&gt;continuous code quality tool&lt;/strong&gt; like &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sonarqube.org/&quot;&gt;SonarQube&lt;/a&gt; provides code coverage as one of its features.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;continuous-code-quality-tools&quot;&gt;Continuous code quality tools&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having automated code quality measurement executed as part of the build process is invaluable. Running automated checks after each code commit is a good way to notify developers of potential problems. Also having a dashboard with detailed quality measurements gives the project manager good visibility of the current code quality and how it is changing over time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the most recommended code quality tools is &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sonarqube.org/&quot;&gt;SonarQube&lt;/a&gt; which has a lot of useful features for detecting various code problems, bugs and vulnerabilities. This feature is called &lt;strong&gt;static code analysis&lt;/strong&gt;. The tool checks the code without actually executing it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While unit tests and static code analysis cover most of the &lt;strong&gt;code quality&lt;/strong&gt;, it is important to measure the overall &lt;strong&gt;software quality&lt;/strong&gt; as well. It is necessary to verify that the business logic is correct, the UI works correctly and the overall performance is acceptable.
This is done using &lt;strong&gt;integration tests&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;UI tests&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;performance tests&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;integration-testing&quot;&gt;Integration testing&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Integration testing means assembly of all the application components and testing the solution as a whole. These tests are more complex and usually are executed on dedicated testing environments. These environments should resemble the actual production environment as closely as possible to avoid any unwanted regression.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Part of integration testing is creating a detailed &lt;strong&gt;test plan&lt;/strong&gt;. The steps in the test plan are closely related to the real world use-cases of the application.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;user-interface-testing&quot;&gt;User interface testing&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the past it was pretty common to test the user interfaces of applications manually. The test plan was a document of steps that the human tester had to follow. Complex business applications required a lot of human testers to follow the test plans and note any possible errors. Nowadays we have &lt;strong&gt;automated tools&lt;/strong&gt; that are much faster and much less error prone than human testers. The most popular tools for testing the user interfaces are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.seleniumhq.org/&quot;&gt;Selenium&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://robotframework.org/&quot;&gt;Robot Framework&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.tricentis.com/&quot;&gt;Tricentis Tosca&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;performance-testing&quot;&gt;Performance testing&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Part of software quality measurements is also performance testing. Performance tests are designed to measure the stability and responsiveness of the application under a particular workload. Using these tests it is possible to investigate the scalability and reliability of the software. The results may have a major effect on the future evolution of the software and could lead to major changes in the architecture of the application.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most importantly, performance tests can uncover many potential issues which could not have been detected by small scale unit or UI tests.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some common tools for automated performance testing are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://jmeter.apache.org/&quot;&gt;Apache JMeter&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://gatling.io/&quot;&gt;Gatling&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;summary&quot;&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this article I have described various ways to manage software quality during the development phase.
I will summarize them in the following points:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Software quality mindset means careful measurement of the quality using specialized tools&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Developers should write unit tests and monitor the code coverage&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Static code analysis tools help with discovering common bugs, code smells and vulnerabilities&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Integration testing is testing of the complete solution in a real environment&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;UI testing is important to verify the user interface and should be automated&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Performance testing can uncover potential stability and scalability issues&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My final advice is &lt;strong&gt;automate as much of this as possible&lt;/strong&gt;. Running these tests could be a part of a complete &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Continuous_integration&quot;&gt;Continuous integration&lt;/a&gt; cycle. I will talk about this in another article. I hope that this article gave you some valuable information on how to measure the software quality and I wish you good luck on your projects!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Miroslav Semerad</name><uri>https://miretz.github.io/about</uri></author><summary type="html">At the heart of the software project lifecycle is the development phase. I have described how projects get to this phase in my previous post on How to start new projects. In this article I’m going to dive deeper into the development phase with focus on how to prevent project failures due to insufficient software quality.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">How to start new projects</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/management/2018/02/13/starting-new-projects.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How to start new projects" /><published>2018-02-13T12:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2018-02-13T12:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/management/2018/02/13/starting-new-projects</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/management/2018/02/13/starting-new-projects.html">&lt;p&gt;In the current world of business, IT is tightly integrated into every process of the company. Each operation is usually supported, controlled or monitored using a specific information system. Payroll, accounting, internal and external communication, human resources, marketing, reporting and other activities rely heavily on IT systems operating correctly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of these systems and many more useful applications started in a form of a software project. 
But what exactly is a project? What are the essential phases and best practices to start a new project?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;project&quot;&gt;Project&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From a high level point of view a project is an individual or collaborative activity to achieve certain goals. This activity involves various tasks like design, research, planning and development which are executed over a period of time. Projects might be long-term or temporary and might be completely operational (like running databases, systems or services).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;idea&quot;&gt;Idea&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the very beginning of a project is an idea. This could be a completely new thing or an improvement of something that already exists. Ideas are actually the easiest step in the project. People who observe the environment around them can come up with a lot of good and relevant ideas. There are also many people who claim that they have the idea for the next “big thing”, but until it is executed, &lt;strong&gt;the idea is actually worth nothing&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ideas don’t have value to investors and even if the person got someone on board, the investment they bring will be worth infinitely more than the initial idea. The original “idea guy” will be left with 1% ownership and 0 control.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a way to give value to an idea. It is called a &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Proof_of_concept&quot;&gt;Proof of concept&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;proof-of-concept&quot;&gt;Proof of concept&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Proof of concept is a validation of a feasibility of a particular idea. This is usually done in a form of demonstration of a prototype to the potential customers and investors. In the real world the creator of an idea must invest his own resources first to develop this prototype. If the product has immediate value by solving a real problem this is a good validation of the idea. However, not all prototypes provide a good basis to estimate future value. For example for a &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Social_network&quot;&gt;social network&lt;/a&gt; website the ONLY value will be actual users. There are many websites with a better idea and better code than the current popular social networks, but without any users. This can be applied to many other software projects as well. Without users the product becomes useless. So what do we do next? How do we know that the project will succeed?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;research&quot;&gt;Research&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is hard to guess if a software project will be successful. We must execute extensive research to ensure that the project has the potential to be successful. I have deliberately put this step after the proof of concept phase. If we already have something in a form of a prototype we can ask for real feedback, use analytics and study usability of the software. With more feedback we can react and introduce improvements and changes. We do it again with the new version and collect even more data. This is an iterative process which has two possible outcomes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We realize that our project will fail - cancel the project as soon as possible, save money, focus on other projects&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We realize that our project has potential - continue with research and the next phases of the project development&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;We can use these data and present them to possible investors. It will give our product much more value that just an idea or a proof of concept.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What if we don’t get any feedback? Consider the following:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We are not targeting the right people - change target and try again&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;No feedback means no interest - cancel the project!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If our project is successful we should continue gathering the feedback in the future. It can save us a lot of time and money when introducing new features or changes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;summary&quot;&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is a short list of the phases and the steps to take when creating new projects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;idea-phase&quot;&gt;Idea phase&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;One sentence summary&lt;/strong&gt; - in 1 hour create a one sentence summary of the project&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Motivation&lt;/strong&gt; - take some time to create a longer description - paragraph:
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Concentrate on motivation: why do you want to start this project?&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Underline the purpose of the project and the desired outcomes&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Do you know something similar, but want to do a better version of it? (How would it be better? Why should users switch to your version?)&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;List of &lt;strong&gt;main features&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Personas&lt;/strong&gt; -  Imagine future users, Remember to stay with why, not how&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Design concrete &lt;strong&gt;user stories&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;proof-of-concept-phase&quot;&gt;Proof of concept phase&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Design the &lt;strong&gt;business logic&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Design the &lt;strong&gt;presentation layer&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Develop a &lt;strong&gt;basic prototype&lt;/strong&gt;
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;focus on main features or particular user stories&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Make sure that the prototype is &lt;strong&gt;fully functional&lt;/strong&gt; for at least one of the user stories&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;research-phase&quot;&gt;Research phase&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Decide who will be your &lt;strong&gt;target audience&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Enable access to the prototype for a sample of your &lt;strong&gt;target audience&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Design and develop techniques to quickly &lt;strong&gt;gather feedback&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Integrate &lt;strong&gt;analytics&lt;/strong&gt; and measure the usage, look for patterns in user behavior&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Act on the feedback&lt;/strong&gt; by improving the prototype&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Iterate&lt;/strong&gt;, unless you realize the project might be a failure&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;development-phase&quot;&gt;Development phase&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the project reaches this phase we could say that the project has officially started. This does not mean that it will be successful, but we minimized the chance of working on something which is not feasible. I will expand more on the topic of software project development in one of my next posts. Thanks for reading the article and good luck on your own projects!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Miroslav Semerad</name><uri>https://miretz.github.io/about</uri></author><summary type="html">In the current world of business, IT is tightly integrated into every process of the company. Each operation is usually supported, controlled or monitored using a specific information system. Payroll, accounting, internal and external communication, human resources, marketing, reporting and other activities rely heavily on IT systems operating correctly.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Why companies need text mining</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/analytics/2018/02/11/why-companies-need-text-mining.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Why companies need text mining" /><published>2018-02-11T16:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2018-02-11T16:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/analytics/2018/02/11/why-companies-need-text-mining</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/analytics/2018/02/11/why-companies-need-text-mining.html">&lt;p&gt;The business world is littered with all kinds of documents which contain important data. Corporate employees have to process thousands of documents every day. Ranging from various contracts, reports, documentation to spreadsheets and receipts. Manual entry into enterprise systems is a tedious and error prone process that does not ensure that the data input really reflects what is in the document.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s explore some typical challenges and some basic starting steps, tools and methodologies that will help companies to handle their document processing tasks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;storage-digitalization-and-records-management&quot;&gt;Storage, Digitalization and Records Management&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many companies still process and store a lot of paper documents. These take up a lot of space and need to be stored in specific ways for easy retrieval if needed. It is very difficult and expensive to set this up, so more and more companies invest in scanning and store the digital scans in &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Enterprise_content_management&quot;&gt;Enterprise Content Management (ECM)&lt;/a&gt; systems.
To turn these scans (which are images) into searchable plain text format an &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Optical_character_recognition&quot;&gt;Optical Character Recognition (OCR)&lt;/a&gt; tool is required.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A global company must be able to handle documents in many languages. Languages like Arabic and Chinese are difficult to process and the company needs to make sure that all the enterprise systems can work with these languages.
&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Unicode&quot;&gt;Unicode standard&lt;/a&gt; should be preferred.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having a &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Records_management&quot;&gt;Records Management&lt;/a&gt; function supported by enterprise systems is very beneficial. Proper RM can help reducing document processing workloads and also helps to filter out the documents that are no longer relevant to the business.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Starting points:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Optical_character_recognition&quot;&gt;Optical Character Recognition (OCR)&lt;/a&gt; - to convert scans into plain text&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Enterprise_content_management&quot;&gt;Enterprise Content Management (ECM)&lt;/a&gt; - to store documents and metadata&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Unicode&quot;&gt;Unicode&lt;/a&gt; - to ensure consistent document encoding&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Records_management&quot;&gt;Records Management&lt;/a&gt; - to manage lifecycle of information&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;searching&quot;&gt;Searching&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reading a 100 page contract to answer a simple question consumes a lot of time. Searching the text for a specific term might lead to the desired information but often it is hard to know the exact phrase to search for. The document might be written in such way that a plain text search does not answer our question at all without understanding the intent and contextual meaning in the document. &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Semantic_search&quot;&gt;Semantic search&lt;/a&gt; is a much better way to solve this issue and it is successfully used by major search engines.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A good starting point is to deploy and integrate an open source search engine, fill it with unstructured data and build analytics on top of it. The most popular search engines are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.elastic.co/&quot;&gt;Elastic Search&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://lucene.apache.org/solr/&quot;&gt;Solr&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;table-extraction&quot;&gt;Table extraction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, tabular data might be easier to be processed by a human. However, if there is a lot of them (imagine thousands of receipts) it can become very exhaustive. Computers are much better at performing these repetitive tasks. Automation of table extraction is the way to tackle this problem. There are some tools that can help:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://tabula.technology/&quot;&gt;Tabula&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://pdftables.com/&quot;&gt;PDF Tables&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/WZBSocialScienceCenter/pdftabextract&quot;&gt;pdftableextract&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These tools are a good starting point to understand extraction of values from tables. The concrete solution really depends on how complex are the documents that the company needs to process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;classification&quot;&gt;Classification&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many business processes are based on correct classification of the incoming documents. The employee must first identify and categorize the document before he can decide what to do with it. With the advent of machine learning, classification of documents became available and much more reliable. The pool of open source and commercial text classification tools is still growing and more advanced techniques based on &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Deep_learning&quot;&gt;deep learning&lt;/a&gt; are accessible and abstracted in high level machine learning frameworks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The data preparation steps are as important as training the machine learning classifier itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are various preprocessing steps used in text classification:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stemming&quot;&gt;stemming&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lemmatisation&quot;&gt;lemmatisation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;splitting to &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/N-gram&quot;&gt;n-grams&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;removal of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stop_words&quot;&gt;stop words&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are 2 common approaches to prepare input for the model:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tf%E2%80%93idf&quot; title=&quot;term frequency–inverse document frequency&quot;&gt;tf-idf&lt;/a&gt; - term frequency–inverse document frequency&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Word2vec&quot; title=&quot;Word2vec&quot;&gt;word2vec&lt;/a&gt; - word vectors&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The model architecture really depends on experimentation and measuring. Sometimes linear models like &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Logistic_regression&quot;&gt;logistic regression&lt;/a&gt; might perform good enough. Other times deep &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Artificial_neural_network&quot;&gt;neural networks&lt;/a&gt; might be a better option providing higher  accuracy. It is up to the data science team to explore the documents, define the preprocessing steps, compare various models, tune their parameters and measure the results.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I recommend these tools as starting points:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://scikit-learn.org/stable/tutorial/text_analytics/working_with_text_data.html&quot;&gt;scikit-learn&lt;/a&gt; - basics of text classification&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://spark.apache.org/mllib/&quot;&gt;Apache Spark MLib&lt;/a&gt; - scalable machine learning library&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://keras.io/&quot;&gt;Keras&lt;/a&gt; - high level deep learning library&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://pytorch.org/&quot;&gt;PyTorch&lt;/a&gt; - deep learning framework&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://radimrehurek.com/gensim/&quot;&gt;Gensim&lt;/a&gt; - topic modeling and text similarity&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;text-mining-and-the-business&quot;&gt;Text mining and the business&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many times companies do not realize how much they depend on their unstructured data. Understanding the information in the documents they process every day should not be an IT goal. It should be a business goal. The new benefits that text mining brings to the table, gives the company not only a competitive edge, but also insights into data they already have. The capabilities to quickly find and process documents is essential in the modern competitive market.
Having a text mining team close to the business helps to modernize many business processes.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Miroslav Semerad</name><uri>https://miretz.github.io/about</uri></author><summary type="html">The business world is littered with all kinds of documents which contain important data. Corporate employees have to process thousands of documents every day. Ranging from various contracts, reports, documentation to spreadsheets and receipts. Manual entry into enterprise systems is a tedious and error prone process that does not ensure that the data input really reflects what is in the document.</summary></entry></feed>